A biblical theology of generosity does not start with tithing, or even Jesus' command
to be generous to the poor.
It starts before time and space, with who God is.
Since the beginning of Scripture, the world itself was created as an act of generous love,
with God as a joyful, generous host, the world as His home,
and you and I as His special guests.
And from the inner nature of God, giving becomes our nature.
And little by little, He makes our souls incandescent.
Well, good morning, everyone.
I hope you all are doing well.
If we haven't had the privilege of meeting yet, my name is Ryan,
and I have the privilege of being one of the pastors here at Canvas Community Church.
And last week, we started our third Practicing the Way practice.
If you're not familiar, Practicing the Way is a church-wide curriculum that we are using within our small groups
aimed at helping us become more obedient disciples of Jesus.
And one of Jesus' most famous sermons, He ends the sermon by saying,
blessed are those who hear these words and put them into practice.
We do not want to be a church who hears the teachings of Jesus, agrees with the teachings of Jesus,
and goes out to lunch and forgets all about it.
We want to be a church of people who take serious the commands of Jesus and through a personal relationship with the Holy Spirit,
look to apply them the way that God is calling them, you and me and us, to apply them.
These practices are not meant to be legalistic requirements to gain some kind of added level of holiness before God.
These are invitations into a deeper personal relationship with God.
And so don't do them if you're just doing them because you think you're supposed to do them to be a good person.
Actually, Jesus has some of the harshest words to say to the Pharisees who are literally so good at doing all of the rules.
They're better than you can ever be at doing the rules.
And Jesus looks at them and gives them some strict, severe warnings because the rules are not the point.
The point is the relationship and the whole person heart transformation.
So that's what we're after with the Practicing the Way series.
And this practice in particular is about generosity.
And I, if you weren't here last week, I gave some disclaimers about money sermons in churches.
So if you missed those disclaimers, I will, I'm sorry.
I, I love to talk about money in church.
Church should talk about money all the time.
Actually, the more you give to our church, the more God, I'm just kidding.
That was not the disclaimer.
The disclaimer is the church has often done a bad job talking about money.
And I just want to make it clear from the outset as we are addressing the topic of money and generosity,
that the goal of this series is not that you would give us more of your money.
We're doing pretty well.
We're paying our bills.
God is gracious.
And when Jesus talks about money, I want you to know very clearly that Jesus does not need your money.
Actually, all of your money is already his.
That he's inviting you to use them in alignment with his kingdom.
And that he's doing that not to take from you, but actually to give to you.
That the teachings of Jesus are going to sound harsh and difficult and challenging to many of us in the room.
And it's because we've been more discipled by our culture.
And the idea is that our stuff is our stuff.
And we deserve to get to use it how we want to use it.
And nothing could be further from the truth.
And so when Jesus invites us into this posture of generosity and contentment and living with open hand as if everything is God's,
it's actually for your joy and for your life.
So those are some of my disclaimers.
Last week we talked about the natural propensity in the human heart to store up wealth.
We like to put it away.
We like to save it.
And we do this because we want to feel secure.
We want to feel safe.
We want to feel at peace.
And Jesus warned us last week that earthly wealth is futile and subject to the brokenness of this world.
It's where moth and rust destroy.
No matter how much you put away.
No matter how much you save.
No matter how safe you think you are.
This world is broken.
And you'll never accumulate enough.
You'll never store up enough to feel truly safe.
His solution was to store up treasures in heaven by living sacrificially and generously.
And he promises that that mindset will actually lead to life.
So if you missed last week, that's where we were.
And this week we're going to turn our eyes to the natural propensity in the human heart.
Not to store up wealth for safety and security, but to accumulate wealth so that we can spend it for our pleasure and our joy.
So just real quick, a fun survey.
If you would consider yourself a saver, raise your hand.
You're a saver.
Okay, decent amount of us in the room.
So last week's message was probably going to be harder for you than this week's message.
Now, if you're a spender, do me a favor.
Raise your hand.
All right, we got some spenders in the room.
Good.
All right, well, it's your turn to sit on the hot seat.
Last week was the hot seat for savers.
This week is going to be, oh, I think what I hear breaking out right now is husbands and wives who sit on opposite.
Is that what's going on?
We got savers and spenders and they're elbowing each other.
Did you listen last week?
Are you going to listen this week?
All right.
So I like it.
There's a felt need in the room for both talks.
This week, we're going to talk about the desire to accumulate things so that we can spend it.
What does Jesus have to say about this pursuit and what solutions might he give us to fight back against this dangerous temptation?
Does that sound like a good plan?
Awesome.
Let's pray.
Oh, Father in heaven.
Everything we have is yours.
True security, safety, peace, and joy is ultimately found in you.
And yet, day in and day out, moment by moment, we will be tempted and drawn away to believe that we can find our own joy, our own satisfaction, our own peace.
Apart from you, God, every day, every day is placed in our lives.
The tree of the knowledge of good and evil, and we are tempted to believe, not to trust you, but to take a bite from the forbidden tree.
God, may this series be a reminder to us that you truly are a loving father, a good, good father who wants good gifts for us.
May we learn to trust you in the midst of our insecurity and our fear and our greed and our worry.
Holy Spirit, make us believe what is true.
Make us aware of where we are believing things that aren't true.
It's in Jesus' name I pray.
Amen.
All right, so a couple months ago, Marissa and I, actually, I guess it was a couple years ago at this point,
Marissa and I were in the market for a new mattress.
And mattress shopping is a pretty serious deal in the Miller household.
We don't spend a pretty penny on a lot of things, but if we're going to spend a majority of our life in a spot, we should probably invest in it, right?
So Marissa and I are debating and looking and sending articles and having this conversation.
And I don't know about you, but when that starts to happen, the rest of my life is inundated with ads for whatever that thing is.
Did any of you ever have this experience?
What's crazy is it's gotten better.
You used to have to at least, like, type it in order for, like, the people who want you to buy their stuff to know that you're looking for their stuff.
Now all you have to do is, like, mention it in a casual conversation to one of your friends, right?
And your feed is filled with advertisements for the thing that you had one conversation about.
For most of us, a huge portion of the content that we engage with on a regular basis, on a daily basis,
is intentionally curated advertisements trying to persuade you to believe that if you just bought the next product,
that if you just went on the next trip, that if you just got the next subscription,
your happiness level would increase.
Executives spend billions of dollars every year on these advertisements.
And these executives, I hate to break it to you,
they're pretty smart and they're good at numbers.
They would not invest the money if it didn't work.
They're spending this money because it's working.
It is persuading us to believe the messaging that they are teaching us.
We are being more discipled by advertisements than we are by the Son of God who came,
lived a perfect life, and taught us how to view our stuff.
The human heart is prone to believe this myth of more.
We look at people above us on the economic ladder and we think,
if I had that car, those clothes, that house, that pool, that membership, or took that trip,
then I would be happy.
Then I would be content.
And here's the crazy part.
The maddening part as a pastor, and just as a human being really,
is the people that you were looking at,
they're looking at the person one step above them in the economic ladder,
and they're thinking, well, if I had that car, that house,
if I was able to go on that trip or join that club,
then I would be happy.
Psychologists call this the hedonic treadmill.
Constantly chasing pleasure.
We hop on the treadmill and we are chasing pleasure.
And yet we arrive nowhere and become exhausted in the process.
And all of my people who don't like to work out are like,
yeah, that's why I stay away from the treadmill.
It's pointless, right?
You get on, you get off, you went nowhere, and you're tired.
This is what we're doing, many of us, as we view our finances.
And the crazy thing is it's not a modern phenomenon.
It's not the executives that are convincing us to do something that humans have never done before.
Listen to the words of Solomon, one of the wisest men who ever lived a few thousand years ago.
He says this, those who love money will never have enough.
How meaningless to think that wealth brings true happiness.
And all of my spenders said, can we get an intermission so I can go to the bathroom and not come back?
Right?
So, with all that in mind, it should not come to a surprise to us that many of Christ's teachings about money,
remember we said last week that Christ, a lot of scholars think that up to 25% of Jesus' teachings are about our money and our possessions.
And in that breakdown, it shouldn't be a surprise to us that a lot of what Jesus has to say about our money is less about what we do with what we have and more about avoiding this myth of more.
More about avoiding buying into the next thing.
The more you get, the better your life will be.
Let's quickly take a look at three of Christ's warnings about this idea of getting more.
Look, in Luke chapter 12, verse 15, his first warning is that greed is dangerous.
Greed is dangerous.
In Luke chapter 12, verse 15, he says,
Beware, guard against every kind of greed.
I don't know about you, but when Jesus says something with an exclamation point, I'm going to listen a little bit more intently, right?
Like, he is emphatic about this, beware, be on guard, look out for every kind of greed in your life.
I love how John Mark Homer, the author of the Practicing the Way curriculum, defines greed.
He says, greed is a lusting for things.
A lusting for things.
It is a transactional interaction between us and stuff.
And we think the more stuff we get, the more experiences we have, the more things we accumulate,
then that longing in our heart will be satisfied.
It's a form of idolatry.
It takes things and puts them on the same level as God or higher in our hearts.
And we can see how this relationship might be dangerous, right?
When we elevate things in our life, it has the power to do a lot of damage.
And this is Christ's warning.
He says, beware, look out for it.
It's dangerous.
As a matter of fact, the statement that Jesus makes here, I'm just going to leave it there because every time I try and fix it, I get louder.
Good?
Okay.
The statement that Jesus makes here is in response to a young man who comes to Jesus, right?
A teacher of the Scriptures.
And this man comes to Jesus and he says, tell my brother to share the inheritance with me.
Now, is Jesus responding to his question at all or is he doing what Jesus does and ignoring the question and getting to the root of the guy's issue?
That was a hypothetical question.
He's ignoring the guy's question and getting to the root of the issue.
He says, beware, guard against every kind of greed.
I think what Jesus is doing here is he's helping the guy see your desire for wealth, your desire for more is putting you at odds with your brother.
This relationship that should be far more important than stuff.
You're coming to me and you're trying to convince me to tell your brother what he should do with the money that's been entrusted to him.
The greed in your heart is actually causing you to value stuff over the people that you're in familial relationship with.
It's important that we notice that there are multiple forms of greed.
I don't know about you, but I am very good at noticing greed in other people's lives, especially people who are greedy for things that I think are silly.
Am I the only one?
Yes.
Man, the more Jay gets to know me, the more comfortable he feels heckling me in the middle of a sermon.
Right?
Like, I look at people who lust for cars.
Like, if it runs, it works for me.
Right?
I'm not a car guy.
And so I look at people who lust for cars and I'm like, they are greedy.
How dare they?
How dare they view such a thing as bringing them value in life?
And then I get an invitation to a private golf club once a week at $120 a clip.
And I'm like, you know what?
I work hard.
I could move some money around here.
Right?
I could find it.
Really?
Right?
Like, I could find some cash and it wouldn't be that big of a deal.
We tend to demonize people who are greedy for things that we find silly.
Meanwhile, we justify our own greediness.
We should all heed Jesus' warnings to be on guard against every kind of greed in our lives.
And focus more on the kind that's in your life and not the kind that's in your neighbor's life.
So, what are some things that you're lusting after?
What are some products or experiences you daydream about getting?
What things do you already have that consume much of your time, energy, and resources?
Greed is dangerous, says Christ.
The second thing he says is that greed is deceitful.
He says that he's talking about the parable of the sower of the seeds.
He's explaining it to the disciples because they didn't know what the heck he was talking about.
I don't know if you've read the Gospels lately, but they often didn't know what the heck he was talking about.
And sometimes he was gracious enough to explain it to them.
And other times he was like, it's not worth it.
You'll figure it out later.
It's fine.
So, this is one of those times where he was explaining it to them.
And he says,
The seed that fell among the thorns represents those who hear God's word.
But all too quickly, the message is crowded out by the worries of this life.
Listen to this.
This is an individual who has received the message of the kingdom of God.
That a loving father creator has initiated a relationship with them.
That they can live for eternal things rather than temporary things.
The greatest message on earth has been given to them.
And they have received it.
And yet, after a little bit of time, this idea of eternity mattering more than temporary things is choked out by their desire for more stuff.
The lure of wealth.
Jesus says, greed is deceitful.
It convinces you that what is less important is more important.
It convinces us that temporary things are more important than eternal things.
Is it possible?
Some of us in this room have intellectually received the message of the kingdom of God.
We agree with it.
We believe it.
And yet, if you look at our lives, our lives are more concerned with the lure of wealth and the desire for things.
Jesus says, the proper response to the kingdom of God is not, yep, that's great.
I love it.
Stuff.
He says, the proper response to the kingdom of God is this.
The kingdom of heaven is like a treasure that a man discovered hidden in a field.
In his excitement, he hid it again and he sold everything that he owned to get enough money to buy the field.
The kingdom of God is so much more valuable than any lure of wealth or desire for more things.
And yet, it lies to us.
Stuff lies to us.
It causes us to believe that it's more important than it actually is.
And we end up wasting our life chasing after things rather than investing in the kingdom of God, which will last forever.
We make bad investments for short-term gain.
Greed is dangerous.
It's deceitful.
And the third thing he says is it's distracting.
Jesus said to his disciples, I tell you the truth, it is very hard for a rich person to enter the kingdom of heaven.
I'll say it again.
It is easier for a camel to go through the eye of a needle than for a rich person to enter the kingdom of God.
This is probably one of Christ's hardest-hitting statements about wealth and greed.
And most of us in the room, when we hear it, are thinking about a person and economic status above us.
None of us think that we're rich.
Right?
But in this Jewish context, rich meant you had access to food and clothing and shelter.
If you have access, this should be a warning to all of us, most of us, most of us in this room have access to the earthly resources we need.
Food, shelter, clothing.
Access to earthly resources distracts us from seeking the kingdom of God, from seeing the kingdom of God as more valuable than accumulating earthly possessions.
It's distracting.
I had a friend who was a youth pastor a few years back in Cary, North Carolina.
Anybody ever heard of Cary, North Carolina?
Apparently, I've been there once.
Apparently, it's like one of the wealthiest counties in the country.
It's like the tech triangle, research triangle of Carolina.
And he was talking about how every single one of his students are rich.
They're loaded.
They all drive like Mercedes and BMWs to high school.
It's crazy.
And I'll never forget the line that he told me.
He looked me in the eye.
I was talking to him about how ministry is going, how church is going.
He looked me in the eye and he said,
Try telling kids who have never needed anything in their entire life that they need Jesus.
This is the distracting nature of stuff.
Those of us that have access to more than enough things,
we lose sight of what matters most.
The more stuff we have, the more stuff we accumulate, the more distracted we get.
The more we're pulled in to invest in temporary earthly pleasures rather than the kingdom of God.
Most of us in this room, we have access to more than the basic necessities of life,
which would put us in the category of rich.
We should take this warning seriously, not to let wealth distract us from his kingdom.
Now, if you're depressed, take a deep breath.
Thank you.
Me and Jay are depressed up here.
All right.
There's good news.
He goes on to say that it's not impossible that anything is possible with God.
And Americans, we need to hold tight to this truth that by the power of the Holy Spirit,
those of us in the room who are most of us, who have access to a lot,
we don't necessarily have to sell everything we have to live in God's kingdom,
but we need to seek to submit everything we have to his purposes.
By the power of the Holy Spirit, with a personal relationship with the Spirit,
we can steward the things that God has given us in a way that builds into his kingdom
and keeps us focused on what is most important in life.
At this point, you might be thinking, I love when I write this.
I have to read this in my notes because I think I'm funnier than I am.
At this point, you might be thinking, does Jesus just warn against the dangers of greed
or does he offer any practical wisdom on how to avoid greed in our lives?
I'm so glad you guys asked that question.
The first passage we looked at in Luke chapter 12,
I stopped it in the middle because I'm cheeky and now I'm going to give you the rest.
Also, I've been watching a lot of Bluey,
so you're going to hear me say cheeky a lot more.
Welcome to fatherhood.
Okay.
Here is the rest of the verse we started with.
Beware, guard against every kind of greed.
Life is not measured by how much you own.
He goes on in Matthew 6,
Seek the kingdom of God above all else and live righteously
and he will give you everything you need.
The word used to describe this attitude towards stuff is called contentment.
And it is the opposite of greed.
This is Jesus' solution for those of us who are tempted to live after the desires of our heart,
to seek pleasure in earthly things.
He says that if we want to fight against that,
if we want to truly live for the kingdom of God on earth as it is in heaven,
we've got to learn to be content with what we have and invest what we have in the kingdom.
I love how Randy Alcorn defines contentment.
He says contentment is being satisfied in whose you are,
who you are,
and what you have.
This is the goal for followers of Jesus,
that we would learn to be satisfied as children of God,
loved, adopted, brought into the family of God,
that we have everything that we need in him.
See, at the heart of much of our greed is the desire to be happy or satisfied,
so we jump on the hedonic treadmill,
chasing after our desires,
and we get nowhere,
and we're exhausted.
So if greed is like a treadmill,
contentment is like a recliner.
That's pretty good.
Come on.
All right.
Thank you, thank you, thank you.
If greed is like a treadmill,
contentment is like a recliner,
let's learn to find rest and be satisfied in God.
I want to look at what the Apostle Paul has to say about contentment
in 1 Timothy chapter 6.
If you want to follow along with me,
we're going to read a couple of paragraphs from 1 Timothy chapter 6
as we start to get practical about how not to chase greed
and to find contentment.
1 Timothy 6, verses 6 through 8.
Paul says,
True godliness with contentment is itself great wealth.
After all, we brought nothing with us
when we came into the world,
and we can take nothing with us when we leave it.
So if we have enough food and enough clothing,
we should be content.
I love how Paul defines contentment here.
He says that contentment is great wealth.
This is the opposite of what we think about great wealth, right?
We think more stuff equals great wealth.
Paul says being satisfied with what you have
is actually the only way to experience true wealth.
True wealth is learning to be content with what you have.
He quotes the famous passage from Job.
Naked I came from my mother's womb,
and naked I shall return.
We all know this concept in our heads, right?
We know that we've all heard the illustration
that you've never seen a hearse hauling a U-Haul, right?
Like, we know it.
You can't take your stuff with you.
It doesn't come with you.
We look at the Egyptians who bury their princes
in pyramids full of stuff,
and we're like, that's silly and outdated and crazy,
and yet we look at our lives.
I look at my life.
Do I actually live as if nothing I have is coming with me,
or do I keep pursuing the next thing and the next thing
in hopes that it will satisfy me?
We all know this concept to be true,
but many of us rarely let it impact the way we live.
Nothing we accumulate for ourselves on earth
is coming with us,
so why should we make it the focal point
of so much of our activity?
One of my favorite verses in the Bible,
Ecclesiastes chapter three, verse 11.
God has placed eternity in your heart.
There's this void inside of each one of us.
We were created for eternal things.
It's why the message of the kingdom of God
is the most important message in all of human history.
It's that heaven is coming back to earth,
that we can exist for all of eternity
in relationship with God,
that we can begin to live for eternal things now.
God has placed eternity in your heart,
and that is why nothing earthly you ever think
will satisfy you, satisfies you.
Contentment is learning to be satisfied with what you have.
I love what Paul says in 2 Corinthians 12.
He says,
My grace,
this is Jesus speaking to Paul,
My grace is all that you need.
My power works best in weakness.
Jesus tells Paul,
Don't worry about living in poverty.
Don't worry about having a physical ailment.
Don't worry about me not answering the prayer
that you want me to answer.
My grace is all that you need.
I will sustain you.
I will satisfy you.
True contentment can only be found
when we accept that we are eternal beings
created for eternal purposes,
and no earthly possession will ever satisfy
the deepest longings of our heart.
He goes on.
Verse 9,
But people who long to be rich
fall into temptation
and are trapped by many foolish and harmful desires
that plunge them into ruin and destruction.
For the love of money is the root of all kinds of evil,
and some people,
listen to this,
craving money,
have wandered from the true faith
and pierced themselves with many sorrows.
I'm not going to spend a whole lot of time here
because I think what we can see here
is that Paul is recapping
a lot of what Jesus already said about greed.
It's dangerous.
It's deceitful.
It's distracting.
It leads us to all kinds of sorrows.
Verse 10.
I want to read that again.
For the love of money is the root of all kinds of evil,
and some people craving money
have wandered from the true faith
and pierced themselves with many sorrows.
It's important here that we point out
that it's not just the pursuit of money
that leads to many sorrows.
It can actually be the success of getting a lot of money
We think,
oh,
it's just the pursuit,
but if I'm really good at making money
and it's not hard for me,
then it won't lead to sorrows.
Jay,
quit preaching my sermon for me, man.
He ruined my joke.
All right,
next line.
We quoted Jesus.
We quoted Paul.
It's time to quote the notorious V-I-G.
Mo' money,
mo' problem.
Right?
It's not just the pursuit of money
that leads to sorrow.
It's the success of money.
John Mark Homer talks about this thing
called the time tax, right?
The more stuff we have,
the more time it takes
to keep up with all of the stuff that we have.
My dad,
I remember when I was like 14, 15 years old,
we didn't grow up with a lot of money.
My dad saved up as much money as he could,
and he bought a $1,200 John boat,
right?
Like metal cast boat
with a little battery-powered trolling motor on it.
Do you know how much money
that $1,200 boat cost?
It did not cost $1,200,
I'll tell you that much,
because every time I looked around,
he was in the backyard
putting money to fix it.
Right?
The more stuff that we have,
the more things we accumulate,
the more time we spend
earning enough money
to pay for the upkeep.
I'm looking at all in my boat,
I'm finding all of my boat owners in the room.
Where are they at?
Right?
We know this.
Motorcycle owners,
whatever it might be,
the more stuff we have,
the more money it costs
to keep up with it.
I almost missed one of my boat owners.
All right, there we go.
I think I got all of you.
All right.
The more we have,
the more exhausted we are
trying to keep up with it all.
Stuff over promises
and under delivers
and it leads us
to many sorrows.
This is Jesus' warning
to all of us
as followers of Jesus.
If you want the abundant life,
if you want satisfaction,
if you want peace,
if you want contentment,
learn to be satisfied
with what you have.
All right,
as we begin to wrap up,
I want to get really
practical here
so that I don't just
make us all depressed
and sad.
Hopefully we can leave
with a smile on our face
if the Holy Spirit
chooses to allow it.
All right,
here's the good news.
If you're in here
and you're like,
man,
I just don't think
I'm a very content person.
It's not that you're either content
or you're not content.
That's the good news.
The good news is that
Paul and the Bible say
that we can actually learn
to be content.
It's not something
you're born with
or born without.
It's something
that can be developed here.
Paul in Philippians chapter four
says,
I have learned
the secret
of being content
in every situation.
We studied Paul's life.
Paul was poor
and in prison.
He says,
content.
Paul had positions
of power
that put him
in relationship
with those
in great authority.
He would sit down
and have the ear
of very powerful leaders.
He says,
if I'm in that situation
or if I'm in
a dungeon prison,
I'm content either way
because I am satisfied
in who I am
and whose I am
and what I have.
Contentment is something
that we can learn.
And I think
the best intentional practice,
the best thing
that we can do practically
to learn contentment
is something
that our Anabaptist
brothers and sisters
call simple living.
Simple living
isn't voluntary poverty,
although sometimes
God might call
some people
to voluntary poverty.
Imagine what the world
would be like
without Mother Teresa,
right?
Sometimes God invites
unique people
into unique situations.
But simple living
isn't voluntary poverty.
It's an intentional decision
to live on less
than what you make
so that you can give
more away
to those in need.
John Mark Homer
defines it this way.
He says,
it's limiting
the number
of our possessions,
expenses,
activities,
and social obligations
to a level
where we are free
to live joyfully
and generously
in the kingdom of God
with Jesus.
I'm going to read that again
because
Frederick County 2024,
this is not
our ideology.
Limiting the number
of your possessions,
expenses,
here's where it gets
real tough,
activities and social obligations
to a level
where you can freely live
freely to live
joyfully and generously
in the kingdom
with Jesus.
If we want to be content,
we've got to stop
asking the question,
what else can I get?
Start asking the question,
what can I live without?
What things has God
given me
that I don't actually need
but I can actually leverage
to help those
who are in need?
I heard an incredible story
from a family
in our church this week,
this is not in my notes
but it just came to my mind,
of a family
that was cleaning out
their upstairs,
they had stuff
that's been there
for who knows how long,
probably longer
than it should have been.
They were cleaning it out
and they decided
to put it
at the front lawn
for free,
right?
One of those things
was a crib mattress
and an elderly woman
knocked on their door
and said,
are you selling the stuff
out front?
They said,
no, it's free,
you can have it.
Turns out that this woman
was driving
through the neighborhood
delivering groceries
for one of the
delivery services
and she's in her 70s,
I believe,
and has inherited
two grandchildren
under one year old
from children
who are addicted.
She's like,
I really need this,
can I have it?
Like, yeah,
not only can you have that,
but what else do you need
and how can we help you?
This is an illustration
of what happens
when we just take
an inventory
of the stuff in our life.
That wasn't even
like a sacrificial ask,
that was just
a cleaning out
of stuff that was,
shouldn't have been there
to begin with.
And God used that
as an incredible open door
for them to be instruments
of the kingdom of God
in someone's life
who is in need
and is struggling.
This is God's vision
vision for your stuff.
Not that you would
get more
so that you can have more,
but that the stuff
that you have
would be leveraged
to help those around you
who don't have as much.
Simple living.
Less about what can I get
and more about
what can I do
with what I have.
It should be done
prayerfully.
Ask the Holy Spirit
to reveal to you
the unnecessary
possessions
and expenses
and activities
or social obligations
that are actually
distracting you
from the things
that matter most.
I'm going to read
1 Timothy chapter 6
going down to verse 17.
He continues his thought here.
He says,
teach those who are rich
in this world
to sell everything
they have
and be poor.
Is anybody reading
along with me?
All right, good.
See, there we go.
It doesn't say that.
Teach those who are rich
in this world
not to be proud
and not to trust
in their money
which is unreliable.
Their trust
should be in God
who richly gives
all that we need
for our enjoyment.
God richly gives
all that we need
for our enjoyment.
Tell them
to use their money
to do good.
They should be rich
in good works
and generous
to those in need
always being ready
to share with others.
By doing this,
they will be storing up
treasures
as a good foundation
for the future
so that they may experience
true life.
Notice,
Paul doesn't say
to Timothy,
teach the rich people
to stop being rich.
If you're here
and you have a lot,
it's possible
that Jesus' invitation
to you
might be
sell everything
and live in poverty.
it's likely
that God would say
you've got to get
a better mindset
around your stuff
and realize
that it's actually
not yours,
that I've entrusted
you with it
to do good
to those
who are in need.
This is how
contentment works.
We start to view
our stuff,
everything that we have,
as a gift from God.
We stop asking,
what else can I get?
And we start asking,
what can I live
without?
I've mentioned this
to you all before.
I have a prayer prompt
that I pray through
every Sunday
that I'm preaching.
And one of the prompts
is that I pray
that this will be
the most fruitful
and effective sermon
I've ever preached.
Some weeks,
it's easier to pray
that prayer
than others, right?
When I'm doing
just like a random
verse study
through Leviticus,
I'm like,
yeah, God,
this is going to be
the most effective
and fruitful sermon
I've ever preached.
I can't wait.
Sometimes it's harder
than others.
This week,
it was not hard
at all to preach this
because I,
or to pray this
because I wholeheartedly
believe that if many
of us would choose
to pursue contentment
through simplicity,
we would be set free
to live generously.
We could have the power
to transform the community
that we live in.
I think many of us
well-intended Christians,
myself included,
we tend to adopt
the spending norms
of the world around us.
Right?
We spend money
the same way
our neighbors spend money
and they spend money
the same way
that their neighbors
spend money
and all of it
is kind of subconsciously
driven by the marketing
of our world.
We're chasing after
the next thing
to find satisfaction
from the next thing
and oftentimes
we just adopt
the spending patterns
of the rest of the world.
Our neighbor gets
a new car,
our car's looking
a little ratty,
we can afford
the car payment
so let's get the car.
Right?
We adopt the spending norms
of the culture around us.
We think because our neighbors
have certain things
or are involved
in certain activities
we should be as well.
We often have a sense
of entitlement
around stuff.
We work hard
so we deserve
X, Y, and Z.
Jay, is it just me
this time or?
Okay, cool.
So, last thing
I'm gonna meddle
just one more time
and it's because
I love you
and it's also
because I love
my future self
and I can see me
buying into this
very quickly
and easily
and so please
receive this in love.
I think many of us
in this room
have heard this sermon
and you're like,
you know what?
I'm not greedy
and I would agree
with you.
You're not greedy
for yourselves
but I think many of us
in this room
are greedy
for our children.
We spend so much time
and energy
and money
to get them
the nicest things
to ensure
that they have
every experience
that they want
to ensure
that they get
to do all
of the things
that their friends
get to do.
We fill our lives
and our schedules
and we stretch
our budgets
in order to give
our kids
everything that
they could ever want
and it's done
out of a good heart.
It's a beautiful thing
in theory
but I think
it's setting
our children up
for failure.
I think we are
subtly teaching them
that true satisfaction
is found in stuff
and in experiences
and in wealth
and I don't know
if you've taken a look
at the economic situation
in our country
but the odds
that they're going
to have access
to enough money
to do the things
that you have
set them up thinking
it's the only way
that they can be happy
and satisfied
and fulfilled
not looking pretty.
Followers of Jesus
we are invited
to teach our children
that true satisfaction
true contentment
true life
is found
in whose
we are
and who God
has made us to be.
What would happen
if we pulled
the emergency cord
on the hedonic treadmill
that we often
find ourselves on?
What if instead
of following
the cultural spending norms
we broke the mold
and truly sought first
the kingdom of God?
What if instead
of using our money
to get more stuff
we chose
to live on less
so that we could
give more away?
Greed
is dangerous
and deceitful
and distracting
but contentment
is where true life
and abundance
are found.
I just want to
remind everybody
once again
I did this last week
if you weren't here
I'm trying to talk
about big picture principles
these messages
will apply to each of us
drastically different.
I'm not trying
to tell you
what to do
I'm asking you
to invite the Holy Spirit
to give you wisdom
to do
what he's calling you
to do.
I want to share
a quick story
I'm listening to a podcast
this week
two guys from
who met
at Harvard Business
getting their
MBA I think
that's a thing right?
Alright cool
I always get these
initials all mixed around
and if I don't put them
in my notes
then I'm afraid
I'm going to confidently
say something
that is not right
so I'm glad
I pulled that out
they both went
to Harvard Business
to get an MBA
they were both
Christians at the time
both making
six figure plus
as 20 year olds
and they both
tithed to their
local church
and they said
we felt like
that was what
we were supposed to do
we were doing
the good Christian thing
10% of our money
is God's
all the rest
of our money
is ours
one of them
was a spender
was a saver
they both
were very ambitious
and had plans
to make a ton
of money
for the rest
of their lives
so that they could
save and retire early
or have all of the things
right
they both had two
very different perspectives
they met each other
at Harvard Business
they took a
class on money
at Harvard Divinity School
as an elective
because they're crazy
I guess
I don't know
seems like a
wild choice to me
but they began
to be wrecked
by what the
Scriptures had to say
about money
and possessions
they realized
that it was
far more holistic
than they had thought
it was less about
just a legalistic task
that they were supposed
to do
and more about
an invitation
to view everything
they had
as a gift
from God
they wrote
a 90 page paper
that I think
was only supposed
to be 20 pages
or something like that
so you know
overachievers
go to Harvard
it's just
it is what it is
but as their
paper started
getting circulated
they both got
a job offer
from a non-profit
who encourages people
who encourages Christians
to view their stuff
as God's
and to give it away
and I don't know
what you know
about non-profits
but non-profits
aren't handing out
six figure jobs
and so they're both
like what is happening
God
like I
I'm going to make
a lot of money
and now that I know
this stuff
I'm going to give it
all back to you
it's going to be great
right
the reason I share
this story
is because they both
got the same job offer
and they both made
very different decisions
based on their
personal relationship
with God
and the Holy Spirit
one
gave up all of
his potential
earning effort
earning possibility
and started working
for a non-profit
because he felt like
that was what
the Lord
was calling him to do
the other
kept climbing up
the ladder
making more
and more money
but deciding
to intentionally
limit the amount
of money
that they spent
on themselves
so that they
could give
more
and more
away
my goal
with all of
these teachings
is not to tell
you what to do
with your money
but to tell
you what Jesus
the big picture
principles
Jesus is inviting
you into
and let you
interact with
the Holy Spirit
in your community
we had a wonderful
conversation
at small group
last week
with a small
group of men
that know each
other
how do you
think
should I do
this
that
one guy
was like
hey
I'm thinking
about buying
a truck
I'm gonna get
your permission
before I do
it
is that cool
I'm like
I'm gonna tell
you no
but sure
if you want
my permission
anyway
my point is
all of this
is invitational
all of it
is so that
you might find
more abundant
life
in obedience
to Jesus
in bringing
about
and investing
in his kingdom
on earth
as it is
in heaven
so
we end
each week
with a practice
last week
was an act
of
spontaneous
generosity
raise your
hand
if you were
able to
participate
in an act
of spontaneous
generosity
last week
some of you
great
if you didn't
get to it
last week
you can get
to it
this week
and you
can do
two in
one week
it'd be
great
this week's
practice
ask the
Holy Spirit
to reveal
a valuable
possession
that you
can either
give away
to someone
in need
or sell
and give
the money
away
to the
poor
this is
invitational
you don't
have to do
it
it doesn't
make you
holier
it's just
so that
you can
interact
with the
teachings
of Jesus
and put
them
into
practice
bonus
if you
want
more
if you
like
that's
easy
I
could
and
don't
make
it
prayerfully
look over
your budget
your possessions
and your
calendar
ask the
Holy Spirit
if there's
anything
you can
remove
from your
life
in order
to free
up
time
to invest
more
time
and more
resources
into the
kingdom
remember
these are
not
legalistic
requirements
but
invitations
don't do
something
out of
guilt
or
religious
duty
do
them
if
you
want
to
take
seriously
Christ's
teachings
to be
not just
a hearer
of the
word
but a
doer
also
let's
pray
father
I've
been
following
you
long
enough
to
know
that
when
you
say
something
it's
true
even
when
it's
hard
I've
been
following
you
long
enough
to
know
that
when
I
drag
my
feet
to
be
obedient
to
the
things
that
you
tell
me
to
be
obedient
to
it
actually
makes
life
harder
and
that
when
I
open
my
hands
and
surrender
to
you
that
the
abundant
life
that
you
promised
actually
follows
it
just
follows
in a
way
that
I
wasn't
expecting
or
anticipating
so
father
I
pray
as we
interact
with
these
difficult
challenging
teachings
for many
of us
about our
possessions
and our
wealth
finances
God
that we
would learn
to have
the
perspective
of
Peter
where
else
can
I
go
you
have
the
words
of
eternal
life
may
we
learn
to be
content
in
all
that
you
have
given
us
may
we
learn
to
invest
first
to
seek
first
the
kingdom
of
God
and
trust
you
with
the
rest
and
God
I
pray
that
another
of us
in
this
room
as
we
go
throughout
this
practice
that
we
would
embrace
your
ideology
of
wealth
and
possessions
that
through
doing
that
God
our
community
would
be
transformed
that
the
needy
among
us
would
feel
our
decision
to
trust
you
with
our
stuff
that
we
would
actually
be
using
it
for
those
in
need
and
that
your
kingdom
would
grow
and
expand
as
people
see
your
followers
obeying
your
teaching
for
your
glory
and
for
our
neighbors
good
in
Jesus
name
I
pray
amen
that
was
long
I
am
sorry
please
stand
and
I
will
bless
you
as
leave
we're
going to
end
every
session
from
this
four
weeks
teaching
with
this
benediction
adapted from
the Scripture
may God bless
you abundantly
so that in all
things at all
times you may
have all that
you need
may you
freely scatter
your gifts to
the poor
may God
who supplies
seed to the
sower and
bread for food
also supply
and increase
your store
of seeds
and enlarge
your harvest
of your
righteousness
may you be
enriched in
every way
so that you
can be
generous
on every
occasion
and may
your
generosity
result in
thanksgiving
to God
amen
go in
peace
church